<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The A, B, C. Or, A catechisme for yong [sic] children. Appoynted by act of the Church and Councell of Scotland, to be learned in all families and lector schooles in the said kingdome.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01430</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A36</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170002</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51784342</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51784342</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174770</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01430)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174770)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2697:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The A, B, C. Or, A catechisme for yong [sic] children. Appoynted by act of the Church and Councell of Scotland, to be learned in all families and lector schooles in the said kingdome.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication taken from Wing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>On t.p.: "Printed by Authoritie ... Cum Privilegio."</note>
                  <note>Some text in black letter.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, Scottish --  Children --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prayer-books --  Children --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:4"/>
            <p>The A, B, C. <hi>OR,</hi> A CATECHISME for yong Children.</p>
            <p>Appoynted by Act of the Church and Councell of SCOTLAND, To be learned in all Families and Lector Schooles in the ſaid Kingdome.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 22.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Traine up a child in the way he ſhould goe: and when he is old, he will not depart from it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by Authoritie. 1644. <hi>Cum Privilegio.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="lists_of_characters">
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">
                  <pb facs="tcp:174770:5"/>A B C D E F G H I K L M N O P Q R S T U X Y Z.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">a b c d e f g h i k l m n o p q r ſ t u w x y z &amp; ſh ſſ ff ſi fi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">A B C D E F G H I K L M N O P Q R S T V W X Y Z.</hi> 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">A a b c d e f g h i k l m n o p q r r ſ s t u v w x y z. &amp; a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſt ſh ſſ ff ſi fi ſl fl () y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>: , . = ? ;</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="roman">ab eb ib ob ub</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="roman">ac ec ic oc uc</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="roman">ad ed id od ud</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="roman">an en in on vn</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="roman">ap ep ip op vp</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="roman">ar er ir or vr</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="blazon">
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:6"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:6"/>
            <head>A Catechiſme for Yong Children.</head>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Qu. WHo made man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Qu. In what eſtate made he him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Perfytly holy in body and ſoule.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Qu. How fell he from the good eſtate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By breaking of the Commandement of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Qu. What puniſhment followed thair upon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Death and condemnatione to him and his poſteritie.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Qu. How are we deliuerid thair frae?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By Gods frée mercy in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Qu. What kind of perſone is Ieſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He is very God and very Man in one perſon.</p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>Qu. Why call ye him verie God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe he is the eternall Son of God, of one and the ſelfe ſame Godhead with the Father and holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>Qu. Why call ye him verie man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe hee is like us in all things, ſinne onely except.</p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Qu. Why was he without ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That hee might bee ane vnſpotted ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for ſinne.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb facs="tcp:174770:7"/>10 <hi>Qu. What hes he done for ws?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He dyed for our ſinnes, and roſe for our righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>Qu. Ar all men that periſhed in Adam ſaued be Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, but onely thoſe that hath true faith in him.</p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>Qu. What call ye true Faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is the true knowledge of Ieſus Chriſt, with aſſurance of ſaluatione in him.</p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>Qu. Rehearſe the Articles of your Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. I</hi> Beléeue in God the Father Almightie, maker of Heauen and Earth.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And in Ieſus Chriſt his onely Son our Lord.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Who wes conceiued of the Holie Ghoſt: borne of the Virgin Marie:</p>
            <p n="4">4 Sufferid vnder Pontius Pilate, wes crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, dead, and buried, he deſcended into hell:</p>
            <p n="5">5 The third day he roſe againe from death.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Hee aſcended into heauen, and ſitteth at the right hand of God the Father Almightie:</p>
            <p n="7">7 Frome that place fall hee come to iudge the quick and the dead.</p>
            <p n="8">8 I beleeue in the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="9">9 The holy Church vniuerſall.</p>
            <p n="10">10 The communion of Saints,</p>
            <p n="11">11 The forgiuenes of ſinnes,</p>
            <p n="12">12 The reſorrection of the body, and lyfe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <pb facs="tcp:174770:7"/>14 <hi>Qu. Be what meanes doth Gods Spirit worke this faith in yow?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the word of God.</p>
            <p n="15">15 <hi>Qu. What call ye the word of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The holy Scripture of the old and new Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="16">16 <hi>Qu. Be what meanes doth Gods Spirit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme this faith in yow?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the ſame word, &amp; by the Sacraments.</p>
            <p n="17">17 <hi>Qu. What call ye the Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They ar viſible ſignes and ſeales ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God for the confirmatione of my faith.</p>
            <p n="18">18 <hi>Qu. How doe they confirme your faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By receiuing thame as pledgis, that Chriſt crucefied (repreſented and offered in thame) is giuen to me in particular to be my Saviour.</p>
            <p n="19">19 <hi>Qu. How many Sacraments is thair?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two, Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p n="20">20 <hi>Qu. Why wes ye baptized being ane Infant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That thereby I might be ingraft in Chriſt, and enterit in his Church, which is his myſticall body.</p>
            <p n="21">21 <hi>Qu. What profit have ye by Baptiſme now?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It ſeales vp the remiſſione of my ſinnes in Chriſts blood; and aduances the reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of my heart in his Spirit: which ar my ſpirituall watching.</p>
            <p n="22">22 <hi>Qu. What call ye the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is the Sacrament of my ſpiritual nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment on the body and bloud of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="23">23 <hi>Qu. How doe ye eat his body and drink his bloud?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By beléeuing aſſuredly that his body wes broken and his bloud wes ſhed for me.</p>
            <p n="24">24 <hi>Qu. What thankfulneſſe owe ye to God for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Son to ſhed his bloud for yow?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I ought to denie my ſelfe, and walk in his Commandements all the dayis of my life.</p>
            <p n="25">25 <hi>Qu. Rehearſe the Commandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> HEarkin and take héed Iſrael, for I am the Lord thy God who hes brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thée out of the land of Egypt, and out of the houſe of bondage:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thou ſalt haue none other Gods but me.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thou ſalt not make to thy ſelfe any gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven image, nor the likeneſſe of any thing that is in heauen aboue, nor in the earth beneath, nor in the water vnder the earth: Thou ſall not bow downe to thame, nor worſhip thame, for I the Lord thy God am a iealous God, and viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the ſinnes of the fathers upon the children unto the third and fourth generation of thame that hateth me, and ſheweth mercie vnto thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of thame that loue me, and kéep my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thou ſalt not take the Name of the Lord thy God in vaine; for the Lord will not
<pb facs="tcp:174770:8"/> hold him guiltleſſe that takes his Name in vaine.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Remember that thou keep holy the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day: ſixe dayes ſall thou labour, and doe all that thou haſt to doe: but the ſeventh day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God: in it thou ſalt doe no manner of worke, thou nor thy ſonne, nor thy daughter, thy man ſeruant, nor thy maid ſeruant, thy cattell, nor the ſtranger that is within thy gates: for in ſixe dayes the Lord made heauen and earth, the ſea and all that in them is, and reſtid the ſeuenth day: wherefore the Lord bleſſed the ſeuenth day, &amp; hallowed it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Honour thy father and thy mother, that thy dayes may be long in the land which the Lord thy God hath giuen thee.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Thou ſalt doe no murther.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Thou ſalt not commit adulterie.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Thou ſalt not ſteale.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Thou ſalt not bear falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Thou ſalt not couet thy neighbours houſe, thou ſalt not couet thy neighbours wife, nor his ſeruant, nor his maid, nor his oxe, nor his aſſe, nor anie thing that is his.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lord have mercie upon us, and write all theſe Lawes in our hearts, we beſeech thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="26">26 <hi>Qu. Which is the ſumme and effect of all theſe Commandements?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, mind, and ſtrength, and thy neighbour as thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="27">27 <hi>Qu. Is any man able to doe theſe things perfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> None at all.</p>
            <p n="28">28. <hi>Qu. Why ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becaus no man is perfitly ſanctified in this life.</p>
            <p n="29">29 <hi>Qu. Yet muſt not we preaſe to a perfectione in fulfilling of Gods Commandements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Doubtles, for otherway is thair is nather faith nor feare of God in vs.</p>
            <p n="30">30 <hi>Qu. What muſt we doe then when we breake any of theſe Commandements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We muſt run to God by repentance and prayer.</p>
            <p n="31">31 <hi>Qu. What call ye Repentance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is the turning of my heart to God with vnfained ſorrow for offending his Maieſty, and a conſtant reſolutione to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my life.</p>
            <p n="32">
               <hi>Qu. What call ye prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is ane incalling of God in the name of Chriſt for things belonging to Gods glory and our neceſſitie.</p>
            <p n="33">33 <hi>Qu. Why is it not lawfull to pray to creatures, as to Angels and Saints glorified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe God hes commandit vs to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip himſelfe alone.</p>
            <p n="34">
               <pb facs="tcp:174770:9"/>34 <hi>Qu. Why muſt we pray onely in Chriſts name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe he is our onely Mediator and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſor.</p>
            <p n="35">
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5 <hi>Qu. How then ſould we pray?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> According to that patterne of prayer that our Maſter hes ſet before vs, laying, when ye pray, ſay:</p>
            <p>OVr Father which art in heaven:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hallowed be thy Name.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Thy kingdome come.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Thy will be done in earth as it is in heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Give vs this day our dayly bread.</p>
            <p n="5">5 And forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as wee forgiue thame that treſpaſſe againſt vs.</p>
            <p n="6">6 And lead vs not into tentatione, but deliuer us from evill: for thine is the Kingdome, the power and the glorie, for euer and euer. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p n="36">36 <hi>Qu. How ar yee aſſured that God will heare your Prayers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By Chriſt is owne word, promiſing that what euer we aske the Father in his name, it fall be giuen vs.</p>
            <p n="37">37 <hi>Qu. What is the fruit of all this your religione and of ſerving God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Hereby God is glorified, and I am ſaued, through Ieſus Chriſt my Lord, to whome be euerlaſting praiſe and glorie. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:10"/>
            <head>Prayers and Graces for yong Children.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Morning Prayer.</head>
               <p>MY gracious God, I bleſſe thée with m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whole heart for thy fatherly providenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> watching over me this night. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> beſéech thée to continue thy mercy with me bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> this day and the whole courſe of my life; to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> end, and in the end: that being alwayes guided by thy grace, and guarded by thy providence, I may ſpend this time of my pilgrimage in thy feare, and end it in thy favour, through Ieſus Chriſt my bleſſed Lord and Saviour. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Evening Prayer at going to bed.</head>
               <p>IT is of thy undeſerved mercy (O God) that I have paſſed this day in ſafetie without ſome notable inconvenience in thoſe infinite dangers wherein I continually caſt my ſelfe through my folly. Now I beſéech thée (good Lord) let it pleaſe thee of thy gracious goodneſſe protect me alſo this night; and grant me quie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſt in ſoule and body, that I may better ſerve
<pb facs="tcp:174770:10"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hee in both, through Ieſus Chriſt my gratious Lord and Saviour. Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will both lay me downe in peace and ſleep: for thou Lord only makes me dwell in ſafetie. Pſ.</hi> 4.8.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Grace before Meat.</head>
               <head>Pſal. 145.15.</head>
               <p>THe eyes of all wait on the (O Lord) and thou giueſt thame thair meat in dew ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: thow openeſt thy hand and ſatisfieth the deſire of euery living thing: (good Lord) bleſſe vs and thoſe gifts which we receiue of thy large liberalitie, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Ane other.</head>
               <p>PArdon our ſinnes (O God) and giue us thy bleſſing with thy benefits, that they may haue ſtrength to nouriſh vs, and wee may haue grace to ſerue thee our gratious God in Ieſus Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Grace after Meat.</head>
               <p>THe God of glorie and peace, who hee creatid vs, redeemed vs, and preſently hes led vs, be bliſſed for now and euer. So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:174770:11"/>
               <head>Ane other.</head>
               <p>MOſt mightie Lord and moſt mercifull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, we yeeld the heartie thanks for o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bodily ſuſtentation requiring alſo moſt intire thy gratious goodneſſe ſo to feed vs with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> food of thy heauenly grace, that we may wort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly glorifie thy Name in this life, and after partakers of thy euerlaſting glorie, throu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ieſus Chriſt our Lord So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Ane other. Matth. 4.4.</head>
               <p>LOrd thow hes ſaid it and we beléeue it, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man liues not by bread onely but by euer word that procéed is out of thy mouth: Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore giue vs (we beſéech thee) thy bleſſing w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy benefits, that in the ſtrength of thy bleſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this life being intertained we may ſpend t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy holy ſeruice, till we a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tain to life everl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſting, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and one<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Saviour. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>To any of theſe or the like Graces that fall be ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> after meat, let theſe or the like prayers be adde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for the Church and for the King, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>GOd ſaue the Church vniuerſall, God co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort the comfortleſſe. Lord increaſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faith, O Lord, for Chriſt thy ſons ſake, by me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifull to the common wealths whair thy Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell is trewly preached and barbarie grant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the afflicted members of Chriſts body, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:174770:11"/> illuminate according to thy good pleaſure all nations with the brightneſſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy word. God ſave our moſt gracious King <hi>Charles,</hi> our Queene <hi>Marie</hi> the hopefull Prince <hi>Charles:</hi> The Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and her Princely Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genie, guide thow thair hearts (O God) by thy grace that they may rule thy people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right to the terrour of euill doers, and the comfort of all thoſe that feares the and loues thy truth. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A briefe of the Commands.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HAve thou none other Gods bot me.</l>
                  <l>Vnto no image bow thy knee.</l>
                  <l>Tak not the name of God in vaine.</l>
                  <l>Doe not the Sabbath day prophane.</l>
                  <l>Honour thy father and mother to.</l>
                  <l>And ſie that thou no murder doe.</l>
                  <l>From whoredome keep the pure and cleane.</l>
                  <l>And ſteale not though thy ſtate be meane.</l>
                  <l>Sie that thou no falſe witneſſe beare.</l>
                  <l>And covet not thy neighbours geare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Lord our ſoules to the convert,</l>
                  <l>And write thy lawes into our heart.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:12"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174770:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
